howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
today's guest is Joe Norman the
freelance complex systems and data
scientist and aspiring homestead farmer
hey Jim how you doing doing real good
Joe has been associated with the New
England complex systems Institute often
identified by the acronym and the CSI
there's published articles with people
there so he's another complexity guy
like me but I must confess I've been at
Santa Fe Institute bigot since I first
read John Holland's adaptation and
natural and artificial systems and soon
thereafter Stuart Kaufman's origins of
order and truthfully I know relatively
little about any CSI maybe Joe you could
give us a short version of your at least
academic life and tell us what Rita any
CSI and what it's about sure absolutely
so just to make it even easier we call
it neck see neck fazer
yup so it's very hard to say and then
moderately hard to say and then easy to
say so neck see is good so I did my PhD
at Florida Atlantic University at the
Center for complex systems and brain
sciences there I studied self
organization of perception dynamics
pattern formation all in the domain of
visual perception after that I was
really looking to expand the scope of
what I was looking at and next he had
caught my interest I had attended of
course there during grad school a
two-week long course taught by uni
herbarium who's the president and
founder as well as Hiroki syama who's
now at Binghamton University and won a
very fine complex system scientist I
will say and you know what really caught
my eye about nexi was an attention to
real-world problems including
engineering and design problems and so
how complex systems not only is sort of
an interesting way of understanding the
world but what it can actually do to
make differences for real problems that
people face so I headed up to nexi at
that point spent a couple years there as
a postdoc I'm currently an affiliate
there and I'm also an instructor at the
real-world risk institute and we also
have an acronym for that our WRI and we
say raisa what are
in there and that's Nassim Taleb school
we run a three times a year at new york
city and i just do a few hours of
lecturing there each time and so that's
another point of involvement with the
complex systems community and its
application to real world issues it
would drew to the study of complexity as
we both know it's a relatively small
field well actually I can say it kind of
runs in the family
my father worked for many years at mitre
corporation and he kind of developed
himself into and really he's a pioneer
in the field of complex systems
engineering so when I was a kid there
was always you know you mentioned Stu
Coffman for instance John Holland these
books were around when I was a kid and I
pick him up and look at them and read
them kind of casually browse them and
you know I was much more interested in
skateboarding but it kind of started to
sink in I think at that point as I got a
little older I started looking during
college at philosophy of mind and that
drew me towards some systems thinking
for instance of Francisco Varela
Humberto Maturana around Auto pieces and
obviously the sort of development of AI
from symbolic AI through connectionism
etc and really I started to link up all
of those ideas what I was naturally kind
of pulled towards and these ideas of
complexity and emergence and
self-organization and so really a lot of
connections start to light up for me
then and kind of just been gradual one
step at a time since then it's
interesting how people take different
paths well my dad was a cop so I never
saw any of this kind of stuff right but
in the later days of my business career
I stumbled on to it's an interesting
story up you know little chance
happenings change one's life I happen to
see a one-paragraph little blurb in
Scientific American about something
called genetic algorithms what the hell
is that I say it sounds interesting let
me look it up I can't tell you the exact
date but it must have been within a few
months of Amazon starting because I
think that one of the earliest books in
my Amazon books ordered is adaptation
and natural and artificial systems and I
read that
whoa is this quite interesting then I
found origins and order read that then
from there I kind of use that parallax
to discover the Santa Fe Institute and
kind of started drilling into that I
started using complexity thinking in my
business career particularly things like
co-evolutionary Fitness landscapes which
actually turns out to be very useful in
thinking about corporate growth and
particularly M&A and then when I retired
I started doing some work that came to
the attention of Santa Fe Institute and
they invited me out there I was gonna go
out for a year as a researcher and
residents ended up staying 10 years and
ended up as the chairman of the place
you know weird things all from reading
one paragraph in Scientific American and
as I hoped complexity science turned out
to be a deep enough domain to keep me
from going back to work that was my real
fear right it's written enough to last a
lifetime of course you know as we both
know there's a lot of things that call
themselves complexity science what do
you describe as a domain of complexity
science that you're interested in well
as I said I'm really interested in this
idea of applied complexity science so
not just the understanding of some of
the themes and features of complexity
emergence self-realization etc but how
do those actually impact our
decision-making so you mentioned an
interesting one coevolution and
co-evolutionary Fitness landscapes so
how does coevolution for example fit
into how we structure organizations what
does that mean for how we expect them to
work and so my current sort of
professional interest is addressing
those questions of ok how do we now go
apply but with respect to what is
complexity science per se you know it's
really stuck on that crystallised the
idea in my mind about what's really
essential about either set of phenomena
we're interested in or a system that
we're interested in or set of objects
whatever may be is that what's crucial
what's essential about them isn't
actually in the stuff that they're made
of as we usually think about it it's
actually in the organization of this
stuff and this started to really click
for me start to make a lot of sense
because you know sort of especially in
the West I'll say we're very much
exposed to reductionism almost as an
underlying where we treat as an obvious
assumption underlying all of our
investigations the way we understand the
world
and for me like I said it was really
Coffman and is focused on organization I
remember he for a time at least used a
term propagation of organization that
really stuck with me and it just lit up
a light bulb in my mind where I said aha
this is really the key they were keying
in on something essential here what
systems are and how they produce
behaviors how they interact with other
systems etc are all really about
patterns and these patterns exist at
different scales so it's organization
organization is really important because
it's about constraints and structure on
interactions so complexity is really
about the way interactions give rise to
phenomena so these are some of the
themes that really capture me and I find
important and essential to understand
the world and some of the more even
currently edged thinking that I'm really
attracted to you know it's performed by
folks like Chris Alexander another SFI
guy where all of a sudden we have not
only are we moving beyond reductionism
in terms of emergence of novel
properties but also the way that whole
systems say a single organism give rise
to what we can kind of part out and
analyze as the parts of the system so
very much unlike the way we construct
systems artificial systems often a
organic and growing complex system
develops and will actually synthesize
its own components functional components
etc and this is very much beyond what
reductionism as a philosophy can really
speak to and so I feel like that's
really where the edge of the thinking is
is how do we now not only have emergent
properties but how do we have things
like functional properties say in the
organ of an organism arising out of not
only that piece of the system but that
piece and how it relates to the context
that gave rise to it and I just feel
that we're only at the beginning really
of grappling with that kind of a dynamic
great I love it I think we must have
come in through a very similar door
because the simple metaphor I used for
people back home to explain complexity
versus reductionism as I would say the
study of the dancer is reductionism the
study of the dance is complexity oh
that's nice that's nice and I really
like that because the
is something that is kind of playful its
organic it's not a recipe it has
structure but it's not sort of pre
formulated and I think that's so much of
what we experience the world is really
the spontaneous kind of cult sort of
game playing or dancing and we don't
really have a great handle on that and
in fact even the sort of structure of
formal systems proper don't play well in
a crucial way with that kind of
spontaneous playfulness that we actually
observe in the world and even built
systems that involve humans have that
attribute even if the designers didn't
intend them to because humans are wilful
little sons of bitches right I worked in
corporate America much of my life half
startups and half big corporations and I
would always tell every new CEO you know
all those buttons and levers that are
theoretically on your desk most of them
aren't connected anything right you can
press all those buttons pull those
levers not a goddamn thing will happen
because the corporate equivalent of deep
state will keep on doing what it's doing
and its own self-organizing
self-interested agency risk fashion and
if they do manage to do anything at all
as you mentioned most likely whatever
those consequences are will be
unintended ones as opposed to whatever
that executive imagined the effect would
be so we just have so many
interdependencies and then subtle
effects and variables and unidentified
relevant variables etc so when you pull
on that lever you think a is gonna
happen and maybe it happens maybe it
doesn't happen but you often get XY and
Z instead indeed the other topic you
mentions one that's also of considerable
interest to me I will say I'm not an
expert in it I probably do need to read
more on it and this is this as you say
cutting edge thinking about the
distinctions between holes and their
components some people I use a phrase
which to my mind is still a little hazy
downward causality that somehow the hole
creates an ecosystem and environment
that supports the existence of the parts
I think actually the reality it's
something even more strange than that
but have you heard of the term down
causality if you have any thoughts on
that oh yeah absolutely I mean downward
causation exactly this is an attempt to
grapple with this issue of well if
emergence is not merely epistemic but in
some sense an to logic then what does it
mean when we say something new emerges
is it somehow contradicting the
lower-level properties if not everything
is arising from them so downward
causation is an attempt to start to deal
with that problem now I also have had I
don't have any strong feelings on
downward causation except I wonder if it
is the right frame and I actually really
like the way you framed it with respect
to sort of a a novel domain emerges that
supports new dynamics that wouldn't be
present otherwise without that domain
now is that sort of top causing bottom
maybe maybe that's not the right way to
think about though maybe it's a you know
emergent constraints and then from those
constraints you can get novel structures
and patterning but I don't have a firm
commitment one way or the other but I do
think it's at that edge that I was
talking about and downward causation is
one kind of key word call it that sort
of signifies that issue that's at stake
I don't know if anyone has done work
that's very convincing on that you know
there's a fellow Eric Cole who has done
some work about using the idea of error
correcting codes and coarse graining to
account for some of that but none of it
that I've seen it has been totally
satisfactory in terms of okay this
really captured the essence and I do
like again what you said in terms of a
developing and emerging domain that then
enables novel dynamics to happen I mean
you think of something like Turing's
morphogenesis patterns right tearing
patterns and you know Turing was really
onto something with that no doubt about
it but what it leaves out is the fact
that the media that those patterns are
occurring on in biological systems is
actually provided by the organism itself
so when the skin se develops into
stripes on a fish those stripes and the
development those stripes can be
somewhat accounted for at least by
reaction diffusion systems things like
that you can think of it as but there's
this kind of interesting causal loop
where yes but it's the organism
developing that's generating the domain
for those Turing patterns so there's
something we're not quite capturing when
we say just look at Turing patterns in
fact I have some unfortunately
unpublished and that's just sort of a
priority stack issue but unpublished
work I'm doing to actually deal with
some of that issue and how
you can think of nested layers of
pattern formation where say a bounded
organism is forming and creating
conditions for other sort of sub
patterns to be generated within that
domain I also think it's hard to get
one's head around until one thinks about
temporal depth right particularly with
respect to natural systems I think one
of the truest statements about biology
is nothing makes sense in biology
without respect to evolution and so if
we think about the whole providing an
ecosystem that has some degrees of
freedom for evolution to work in we can
start thinking about this whole in parts
coevolution essentially right so you can
look a series of generations don't look
at a static developmental framework in a
short period of time but rather you know
multiple generations you know the whole
provides some degrees of freedom for the
internal parts you know person's liver
can be bigger or smaller without killing
them though it probably had some impact
on their phenotypic afib Nisour so you
know there's some changes at the top
let's say the organism and all of its
components including its brain and its
social systems discover a new way eating
right or find a new food that's richer
in things that are good for the liver
and so the liver can get smaller and so
less of our energy is spent on liver
function and more can be spent on brain
function so you have over a time depth
you have a very interesting coevolution
going on between the phenotypical full
organism level and its structural
components that's absolutely true and
you know one of the things that Kaufmann
really hammers home is that these sort
of functional roles that different
structures play over that evolutionary
time are pretty fluid in in the sense
that just because a structure plays
function a today doesn't mean it
couldn't play some other function
tomorrow and a striking example of that
is the jaw bone in our long distant
lizard-like ancestors at some point in
evolution it began to become perhaps
we're not sure but perhaps vestigial in
the sense that it became small and not
responsible for articulating the jaw
anymore and there was another bone that
evolved that did serve that function but
the structures didn't disappear what
they did is migrated towards the sort of
where our in
year now exists and became our inner ear
bones that allow us to transduce
pressure waves into nerve impulses
otherwise known as hearing so it's
something that was once for the mouth to
open and close became later for hearing
which seemed worlds apart yet evolution
doesn't mind it will kind of grab what's
available and through that process of
coevolution discover really interesting
novel functional purposes and this is
something of practical import so you
mentioned that you found coevolution
really useful for thinking about state
organizations and this is because things
like this can emerge and they're not
something that anyone would necessarily
imagine they're not necessarily even
priests a de belen in terms of state
space which is a really interesting
possibility so exactly right unless we
look at the fullness of time we don't
really have a good handle on these
things so I guess another piece is I
sort of hinted at it but it's really
essential for me to think about complex
systems is that we're always really
facing patterns that exist at multiple
scales so that's multiple spatial scales
that's also certainly multiple time
scales so that functional fluidity I
think is huge and it also speaks to the
way we think about engineering say in
terms of imagine someone engineering the
organism that became us and at some
point they said I don't really
understand what these old jaw bones are
doing so let's actually optimize them
right out and make this system much more
optimal because it's wasting resources
and well you know if that had happened
then we would have missed the
opportunity to hear yeah absolutely and
it turns out my actual deep scientific
expertise is in evolutionary computation
and we see this all the time and let's
say genetic programming right if you
don't manage your genetic program which
is essentially a way to evolve programs
right you start with sort of random
programs and you do cross over a
mutation you get better programs to
solve problems and you can quickly get
bloat where you get lots and lots of
what seems like dead code and as you say
there are optimization algorithms one
can do in fact you can actually just put
a very heavy tax on length and that will
cause evolution to select for shorter
programs and had squeezed out most of
the bloat but it's now well-known that
if you squeeze out too much of the bloat
you don't have enough pieces so you know
I'm
diversity for future evolution so
there's a subtle balance between
sufficient diversity versus no diversity
on one side and bloat which takes too
many of your resources and here it is
Ana pure software evolutionary
environment and as you say it fits in a
very analogous fashion with real-world
evolution of animals well that's
fascinating Jim I didn't know you were
working on that that's really cool stuff
and you know as you talk about it the
thing that comes to my mind is okay so
there's sort of the temptation is to say
well maybe there's kind of a sweet spot
for that variety you know like you said
if it's too much blow to just cogging
your resources if it's not enough it's
not developing those opportunities and
those two those kind of adjacent
Possible's but then perhaps maybe there
isn't even an optimal there but in the
bigger bigger picture perhaps that's
also a variable that requires diversity
some environments are more supportive of
bloat and some environments are less
support of upload so you kind of get
variety and then met a variety you might
say and so all of these ideas I think
are so essential for how we're going to
build systems into the 21st century
because we're pretty much beyond the
point of being able to structure many
systems in a sort of top-down
intentional way so that's really cool
I'd love to talk to you more about the
computational evolution stuff that's
very nice that's very cool stuff that's
really what I did in this field mostly
as you say that that cause I'm just
gonna think out loud here which is
allowed on the show frowned upon in real
life but on the Jim Rutte show we allow
thinking right when you say diversity of
bloat what that actually means is
probably the lack of tightness in the
ecosystem typically and let's say the
natural system and then I'll give you
the computational equivalent when a
let's say a major new innovation happens
let's say fish come out onto the land
right suddenly they have this
unbelievably cool ecosystem that they
can pillage and grow and reproduce
extremely rapidly with no limits for a
while but we go back to Malthus and
sooner or later you reach the carrying
capacity of the ecosystem and we have no
extra resources really and inevitably in
stasis most species are living on the
edge of starvation all the time so
during those pioneering periods bloat
would conceptually be okay right at a
couple different levels right one
because you don't have to worry about
starving which is always the number one
risk you can be a little bit less
efficient you can carry around more
extra components and when the times get
tight jeans that are bloaty get selected
against because they're consuming more
calories per unit of reproduction and
get squeezed out you know I would you
know say the same is true when trying to
solve a problem in genetic programming
to agree that the ratio of the hardness
of the problem to the amount of
computation you have seems weighted on
in the side of having lots of
computation I would hypothesize thinking
out loud here I may actually do the
experiment that being more blody is good
if the job is to solve the problem in
the shortest period of clock time on the
other hand if it's a really hard problem
and you don't have an unlimited
computation budget then one must think
more about optimizing bloat for the
search space that you're in don't make
any sense yeah that absolutely makes
sense and I'd love today if you end up
running the experiments I'd love to have
a look and then talk about them and you
know I guess the challenge is and once
again now I'm just sort of going out on
a limb here and I would need to think
about it more to have confidence but I
almost wonder if the question itself is
undecidable in terms of a priori do I
know how much bloat
this problem deserves so to speak and I
wonder if we can answer that a priori in
any reasonable fashion I think we can
into it in many cases kind of where that
balance might be struck but whether it
can be solved once for all I'm not sure
I'm actually quite strong on that you
cannot to solve it for sure forever and
why the no free lunch theorem David
Wolfe pert one of our SFI guys earlier
in his career before he came to SF I
formulated the no free lunch theorem
which is one of the most important
theorems in the universe and in fact I
divide people the people who know and
practice the no free lunch theorem and
those that don't
essentially what Wolfert prove
definitively is in an arbitrary space
there is no optimal search strategy
every search strategy has to be
optimized for the search space that's
being applied to and I would turn your
words around and say that you may not
have
explicitly brought to mind no free lunch
but you intuited it when you said you
apply your intuition to tune a search
algorithm for a search space and that's
what you do really there is no right
answer for searching any given arbitrary
search space that's a great way of
thinking about I love that okay I mean I
have to bring more attention to the no
free lunch theorem love it it's
amazingly short readable paper but it to
my mind is actually fundamental if you
don't know the no free lunch theorem you
don't actually understand the universe
that we happen to be living in so I'm
glad I could offer that up the folks to
read david wolfe / wo lper t another
thing I saw in some of your writings as
I was reading them getting prepared for
this chat is that you tend to use the
word irreducibility quite a bit you know
some schools of complexity do some don't
I'd love to have you define that for our
audience and keep mine they're smart
folks but mostly not with backgrounds in
complexity science well I will say that
when I use the term irreducibility in
general I'm using it somewhat
colloquially in the sense of I'm not
referring to a specific kind of
irreducibility necessarily but rather
the general concept of irreducibility
and what I mean by that is you could
have for instance a a very specific kind
of irreducibility such as computational
irreducibility that Stephen Wolfram
talks about in that case he's really you
know all his work is founded on
elementary cellular automata and the
fact that they present a universal
computer and so you can kind of think
about essentially any process that is
computable in that framework and in that
frame a reducibility can sort of be
summarized by saying well there's no
shortcut to the future to see how the
pattern unfolds in time or what it will
be at some arbitrary time in the future
you have to go through every step so
everything in the in his world is
discrete time discrete space cellular
automata deterministic nevertheless even
with all that determinism in the system
there's no concise sort of compressible
formula to say well what will happen at
time 1 billion or 10 billion or ever it
is so it's irreducible in the sense that
the whole pattern determines what
happened
in the pattern in the future and there's
no shortcut so that's sort of a summary
of computational irreducibility but it
really gets at this idea of
irreducibility more generally which is
the idea that there's no further amount
you can deconstruct the system into
smaller pieces or fundamental laws or
something like that that allows one to
impress the system further say sort of
compress it to something a redundant
pattern or a repetitive pattern say that
allows one to kind of project in time or
space
what will the system be what will it do
how will it behave and so I mean it
comes up in other places like in
cybernetics irreducibility has to do
with essentially matrices and whether
they can be broken down their machine
can be broken down into smaller sub
components that behave independently so
that's the general idea and I just like
the term irreducibility
because it really puts emphasis on that
issue of you're looking at some
phenomenon and it's as far down as you
can get to address that phenomenon and
if you go any further you actually
destroy that phenomenon via the analysis
that's the very similar to the
computational measures of complexity
right is there any shorter way to state
a problem than to just run the program
write write write a halting problem of
course absolutely yeah and you like to
Wolfram I played for a while with rule
120 to see if I could find anything
there and the answer was no right
[Music]
interesting stuff another sort of key
fundamental building block of
conversations around complexity
emergence I'm sure you've thought about
that a little bit you know I've some of
the things I found most useful there are
Harold moretz's book the emergence of
everything and he lays out like 28
levels that's gonna start at quarks and
work their way up to the universe and
again John Holland is very difficult
book but a very one worth reading
emergence from chaos to order who do you
follow who have you read what do you
think about emergence all and I've
certainly read Holland we've already
mentioned Kauffman I really enjoy Chris
Alexander who has some technical chops
but often takes a sort of informal
approach to these issues because he's
really thinking about the practical
space of architecture in his case but
his insights really applied to so many
kinds of practices so everywhere from
from sort of folks that have a formal
treatment you know Robert Rosen is
somebody who I feel doesn't really get
enough credit and and he deals with some
of these issues with biology and the
limits of formalism so I look at all
across all these folks I try not to
commit myself to what kind of one
treatment or another but instead try to
get a kind of just alt across the space
of what is everyone saying in common
where the difference is I think what's
so essential and does kind of cut across
all the different treatments is the
relationship between formal models and
what happens in the world and so much of
what we experience is emergence and this
once again this comes across even folks
who either believe emergence is merely
epistemic meaning it's not really
happening but according to how we
understand things we need to invoke it
to help us understand what's going on to
those who are more like a Kaufman who
believe it's ontological and you know
new things properties arise in the
universe that are novel proper I'm very
much interested in a practice oriented
approach to emergence where we can kind
of start to think about how do we react
locally to local perturbations local
variables and respond incrementally
essentially to small pieces of
information we gather from the system as
we interact with a perturb it and it
kind of pushes back or gives us feedback
and out of these very small incremental
movements how things that we don't
imagine or organizations that we never
imagined or explicitly designed to come
out of the system that were generally
embedded in and interacting with you did
mention upfront that one of my current
pursuits and hopefully a lifelong
pursuit is the idea is homesteading
and this has been a really embodied
experience for me since my wife and
myself moved - up to live in New
Hampshire now and we got a little
property where we're doing the stuff
we're growing our own food you know
we're not able to provide all of our own
food but day after day it's more and
more making progress and really there's
no where we are now even after a year of
doing this we've pursued the process for
multiple years we've been living on this
property for a year now I wouldn't have
known what to do even simple things like
where do I put this fence where do I put
this gate where do I put this garden bed
where do I fell this tree why this tree
why not that tree all these little tiny
decisions over time are actually
evolving into systems of behavior that
were embodying where there's server
merging semantic relationships out of
the different pieces and parts of the
property oh this is the part where the
compost collects and and it's uphill and
that's useful because you know until we
collect the compost to spread somewhere
intentionally it's now running down the
hill into the garden so it's even
passively helping to fertilize the
garden beds things like that small
things here and there are things I
didn't imagine up front and couldn't
have designed but they're emerging out
of our small incremental interactions
over time yep that's really entering and
just as an interesting isn't the world
strange I originally ran across Joe and
a friend of mine said hey you oughta
talk to Joe Norman he's a smart guy
interested in local agriculture I had no
idea it was a complexity dude how about
that it's a beautiful intersection
there's not enough of it there is some
and especially in when you do start to
look into the local AG even without it
being explicitly called out so many of
the insights of complexity are embedded
in there and you know for instance in
permaculture and some of these other
philosophies we had Joel Salatin out at
the Santa Fe Institute one time that was
quite interesting I loved you all I'll I
mean I haven't met him in person but I
love his writing so that's really cool
that must have been fun Joel's a
neighbor we live close to Joel we know
reasonably well
run into him fairly frequently so he is
an amazing character a true American
innovator in his books are well worth
reading my favorite is everything I want
to do is illegal
great title and that's a really
interesting book and he is right at the
cutting edge of helping to rethink what
local agriculture might actually mean
though I will say we did not really
successfully inoculate him with the
complexity virus but it maybe helped us
perceptions a little bit he certainly
helped our perceptions a little bit by
bring in more practice oriented things
you know more in the applied space I'm
gonna jump here a little bit when I was
preparing for this I liked their prepare
5 to 10 hours for each guest and one of
the things I ran across was your
dissertation and I read that with
considerable interest that was on the
perception of objects in motion and I
particularly liked the fact the
irreverence one of my favorite cognitive
scientists who actually sort of became
an anti cognitive scientists later
JJ Gibson if you're up to it maybe talk
a little bit about you know what you
learned in doing the work for your
dissertation oh yeah absolutely
yeah so JJ Gibson is wonderful he is
you know his most famous book is the
ecological approach to visual perception
what he means by ecological is not
necessarily the way you think of ecology
in terms of all we're looking at
interactions of organisms like that but
the fact that the living human or any
living organism with vision in this case
is embedded within an ecological system
and that has some profound implications
for how we think about perception you
know one of his key concepts is this
idea of affordance and an affordance is
a we could call it an atom of perception
that is action-oriented or implies some
set of possibilities for action so his
idea is we don't perceive abstract
physical properties of the environment
we're not gathering census data to
reconstruct a kind of physical theory of
what's out there but rather what we're
doing is picking up opportunities for us
to act on the environment or within the
environment so you might think of
something like a branch is graspable and
so you don't see that the branch is you
know approximately cylindrical
something like that you see no I can
actually grab that with my hand and pull
on it and pull myself up this tree so
it's it's very much an action-oriented
heuristic kind of you might think of
base idea of perception and what this
really starts to draw out is that what
we think of as perception is really a
relational property so we often again
from from this kind of Western
reductionist to Canon think of okay we
have a brain and inside that brain we're
modeling the world out there but when
you think about what does it mean for a
branch say to be graspable well now I'm
invoking the structure of the organism
itself as well because there's a
relationship between say the size of the
branch and the size of a hands that can
grip it these are some of the ideas that
JJ Gibson introduced and are so powerful
and really can affect the way you look
at the interaction of organism and
environment and what it means for an
organism to be structured and what that
means for the experience and the and the
perception of the organism and this is
also related to ideas of like um felt
like a like an animal or a species as a
certain kind of life world that they
inhabit and that life world is with
respect to the structure of the organism
itself now how this worked into my
dissertation I actually in large part
included JJ Gibson in my dissertation as
a nod to where I felt I fell short which
is I did a lot of psychophysical
experimentation looking at perception of
motion of folks sitting and looking at a
computer screen and having some frames
flash and asking them if they're able to
discern shapes what they saw with
respect to patterns of motion and I
think I uncovered some really important
things doing that but at the same time
there was an ever-present awareness that
this is not like an ecological setting
there's something much different about
sitting in a testing room looking at a
computer screen and answering questions
now I will say that to do justice to
that setting that is itself an
ecological setting of a kind but one
needs to always maintain the awareness
that that is a very specific a very
special setting and not a general
setting and there are in fact some
features of more general settings that
might be important to and certainly are
important to understand how
what I was discovering really is
important or not important perhaps to
ecological perception so what I looked
at was the way that looks at several
things but for instance the way that
certain patterns visual patterns are
multi stable so you can show the same
pattern to either different people or
the same person at different times and
what they perceive is different one time
versus another so we looked at the
dynamics of that we looked at some of
the older literature we spoke to in
psychophysics that did some poor
statistics frankly and assume some
things that were not quite right should
know there's different kinds of visual
information that people are using for
different kinds of processes and really
showed that the response is quite a
nonlinear one and you can capture a lot
of very different seeming stimuli with a
concise model and i/o at design model to
a dynamical neural network into showed
that a very generic pattern of
interaction among the neurons in the
neural network exposed to patterns
looked a lot like I'll say very very
close to what people perceive across
these patterns and that connected it to
the old psychology with respect to sort
of perceptual principles and embody
those principles is something a little
more hard coded say in a mathematical
and computational model yeah I found it
very interesting because my biggest
single personal project is building a
rudimentary conscious cognition embedded
in an ecosystem modeled on a
white-tailed deer and I used Gibson as a
significant part of my inspiration I
thought of what you were doing as the if
it's true well someday maybe find out as
one of the building blocks on which
these phenomena are built so I didn't
specify down at that level I'm working
at a higher level and I assume something
like that is going on which delivers
into the global work space objects and
set of affordances which are actually
discovered over time relationships
motion etc and so it was like right
next-door neighbor of the work that I do
and I said wow you know I wish I'd read
this when I first started working on it
might have built a little bit more down
in that direction oh that's interesting
you know there's two directions that if
I had continued on that particular path
I was planning to pursue and things just
change and I didn't put any more time
into them but one was indeed that okay
let's start embedding this in Asians
that are in an environment and exactly
that so let's start to see if they can
discover affordances the other was the
fact that I've looked at these things so
often that I became very good at
controlling what I was perceiving so
most of the subjects were sort of you
know that they experienced it as a
passive reception of they either saw
this or they saw that whereas I could
decide in real-time what I was seeing
and I started to run some experiments
that showed that there were definite
time scales at which this did happen
over and therefore it also didn't happen
over and they were different than the
time scales of the perception itself
sort of just to say it quickly if the
motion patterns were too fast you can
still perceive the motion but you could
no longer control it
whereas if that you slow them down to a
certain critical speed you could start
to actually control which pattern you
were perceiving and I think that this
has some there's some deep connections
between these two as well and with that
question of perceptual learning and how
we discover affordances over time I can
give you a great perceptual learning
example and once it happened to me about
seven years ago I've been extremely
interested in perceptual learning you
know as a farmer myself every spring I
spend about seven to ten days
eradicating invasive weeds that are
trying to attack my field spring
specific invasives right and they were
coral berry Barbary and autumn olive
right and after seven to ten days of
riding around four or five hours a day
in making a real-time decision on which
is one of those three species before he
has a pit when I was near done with it
as I dried up the roads in a nearby town
any invasive species in people's field
it's just like blinked at me it was
amazing all right they just popped it
was an astounding you know just really
strong example of perceptual learning
and since then I've taken the perceptual
learning literature much more seriously
than I ever did before that's right and
once again just to draw on my recent
experiences of beginning the homestead
lifestyle is just that when I first got
here Jim I didn't even want to like clip
a branch I was like what am I gonna
screw up if I clip this branch and over
time I'm developing the perception of
sort of seeing out in time a little
further where I can see you know if I
let this thing go where will it kind of
tend to go if I clip it now what will
tend to happen say around it's gonna let
more light in and things like that so I
think that perceptual learning is really
essential and it's fascinating the way
we kind of have to step into the unknown
because you can't know what it's like to
perceive something you haven't perceived
yet so you have to continue to put
yourself into the situation over and
over where these kind of serendipitous
moments can happen where something
clicks inside of you is it's certainly
some kind of a self organizational
process can't be top-down directed but
something snaps and all of a sudden you
can see something you couldn't see
before
you'd have a tool that the higher-level
systems can use also which is you know
what's that perceptual learning is
clicked in you can operate much more
rapidly and targeting your invasives
anyway let's flip back now to talking
about complex systems and one of the
things that you know it did trigger some
thoughts in my head as I was reading
your dissertation is the relationship
between complex systems science and
modeling and simulations you know some
people say hey you really can't do these
probes on complex systems and at some
level they're correct but at other
levels they're not I mean we hit we do
do probes on complex systems with both
models and thinking through the
implications of models and sort of more
quick and dirty with simulations have
you given any thought to where model
building and simulations fit into the
explorations of complexity science yeah
absolutely and so from an applied
perspective we're really trying to solve
a problem understand a system that we
need to interact with better that we're
trying to get something from I think the
number one utility to modeling is to
make assumptions very explicit so we
have to if we want a computer simulation
to run we have to write down what are
the assumptions that are being made so
that it can unfold its behavior at time
making those assumptions very explicit
and then when we go back to the system
to observe the real natural system
determining
we've made those the right assumptions
so you know modeling and simulation is
often considered in the paradigm of
prediction sort of build the model run
it forward a time and predict what's
going to happen there's a lot of
problems with that it can work under
certain conditions but I think that
that's a secondary kind of a utility of
modeling and really this primary utility
is to didn't we get the assumptions
right you know agent-based modeling I
think one of the really powerful aspects
of it is that because we're able to make
a large set of micro assumptions we can
actually see the difference in the
aggregate behavior between what unfolds
from that agent-based model and what
maybe we would have thought would unfold
if we did some more macro level formal
modeling say for example say we're
modeling a hospital and looking at how
infections might propagate through a
hospital you know there's there's this
issue where you go to the hospital and
you're trying to get better but you
might pick up an infection while you're
there because there's a lot of other
sick people around and whatnot so let's
say we're modeling that and if we want
even AG based model we could say okay we
can model a surface we can make some
assumptions about if someone touches the
surface and they have say this bacteria
on their hand maybe there's some
probability that it transfers to that
surface now someone else comes to the
service so we can model really at that
very micro level where our assumptions
are actually probably pretty good
relative to our macro assumptions
whereas if we wanted to do some
high-level mathematical modeling of that
system we might assume something like
for instance that some set of events are
independent like my touching a surface
and you're touching a surface are some
kind of independent events where they
might actually have interdependencies
and therefore follow different kinds of
distributions and so that's just to give
a little bit of crystallization to this
general idea that really we are the
worst at understanding our own
assumptions and identifying where
they're faulty and modeling and
simulation can allow us to draw them out
force them to become explicit and give
us an opportunity to adjust them as we
observe the real system the natural
system I like that way of thinking I may
add one additional thing which I often
do when people are talking about models
agent based models or physical
simulations which is a
one side it helps you clarify your
assumptions and on the second as you
pointed out one should not believe any
given subject area right however I do
believe that once a model has been well
developed and the assumptions vetted by
experts and by the best available
evidence one can often learn some
interesting things from ensemble
statistics of large numbers of runs
right for instance we can find out if
we're in mediocrity and/or extremists
and in the NNT type language right we
can see how much variance is there
between the runs because the beauty of
agent based models if they're not too
big you can run them a million times
right you can really get a sense of what
statistical distribution of outcomes are
we likely to see with this set of
assumptions I add that it's something
that people often miss when they think
about what can you do with simulations
or models that's right and I would never
take a model too too seriously that
didn't have some stochastic City
involved so that you run it you know
many times over and look at the in Samba
that said there is always the danger
that even across those who say build
models in principle it seems like
independently there are subtle ways for
non independence of assumptions to arise
you might think of something like
climate science where you have many
different teams many different
individuals building models and some of
the way they're structured some of the
factors they incorporate are different
so there's some independence among how
they're instantiated nevertheless
there's a cultural I almost a cultural
climate maybe that's a little confusing
oh well that can inject more subtle non
independence into the Assumption set and
so even when we do have a nice model
even if it's very robust I'm always
always always hyper cautious of
committing too much to any action that's
solely coming out of a modeling
prediction even on an ensemble but I do
agree with your main point that yeah
we're not talking about you know run
them the deterministic model for it in
time and think that's how the system
goes no the real world is always messier
than that and ensembles are the right
way to think and even interestingly
which you know you mentioned NNT the
same we often think of running ensembles
so that we can think of the distribution
of possibilities into the future but we
actually have a lot of uncertainty about
the past as well and thinking about the
past in terms of ensembles actually
makes a lot of sense - we only have one
past we only have one but this is about
knowledge of the past and it's actually
very difficult to transmit you know
perfect fidelity what actually happens
in any given situation and in fact if
you take seriously the idea of just just
think of a simple fixed point attractor
and if say more than one path you know
converges any kind of many to one
mapping then in principle we can't say
which paths led to it now we might have
some nice evidence where we can
reasonably say but as a general point
it's a real problem with understanding
kind of where we are where we come from
interesting yeah you could run the
simulation backwards you know it won't
give you the answer but it will give you
a set of things some of which could be
close to the answer right exactly that
is actually pretty interesting what do
you think of climate science I know
you've written a little bit I saw your
one-pager that you wrote with some other
folks what are your thoughts about
climate science and how we should think
about it and how we should think about
as we know a fair amount of the argument
is based on modeling where is your head
as a complexity applied the complexity
guy around climate science well you know
the letter we wrote was really a
companion piece to our larger piece on
we call non naive precautionary
principle and with respect to climate
we're sort of making a point that I
think is essential for someone to be
making and we have this kind of
polarized discussion where we're saying
they're sort of the believers and the
deniers and the believers say here's
what the models are saying here's the
scientific consensus they're saying so
here's why we should be worried about
climate and the deniers are saying you
know this is funded agenda or this is
the models are bunk and so we shouldn't
be worried about it but the interesting
thing is we all can agree that the
climate is important if it goes outside
a range
becomes too volatile and that's very bad
for living systems including us and all
of the life support systems we depend on
so the implication of having poor models
that do a bad job predicting is not at
all well don't worry about it then it's
actually the opposite it says if we
really have trouble predicting this
system and we don't know what's going to
happen then we should probably exercise
an abundance of precaution around this
system and we should do what we can to
mitigate our contribution to the
unpredictability and in this case that
contribution could be say a large
coherent expulsion of co2 and you know
we don't need to necessarily understand
the exact trajectory of dynamics that
one fold to know that if you have a
complex system if it's large scale in
this case if it's essential for life and
if you perturb it with a large-scale
force say a lot of co2 coming out at
once then you're easily contributing to
the destabilization of what is likely a
metastable system so that's our
cautionary principle approach to the
climate problem and the more uncertainty
we have around the models the more we
need to move forward with an abundance
of caution and not assume that oh well
you know if the models aren't great at
predicting then we're fine don't worry
about it and I would also add this is a
Mary always look for is get away from
just data and look at causality there is
a base causality around climate which
everybody needs to keep in mind which is
it's an absolute easily provable
physical-chemical
finding that if you build a system and
add greenhouse gases into it and radiate
light into that system and have it
reflect back as infrared more energy
will be stored in the system that has
more
greenhouse gases so that's a very
important base fact which some of the
deniers don't even seem to know right
that is true and the question then
becomes from my perspective what are the
other agents in the system that might
then start feeding back and alter that
particular trajectory so for instance
like Freeman Dyson that has talked about
well the earth is greening and you know
you have all the co2 the atmosphere that
means that plants grow more easily so
the earth is greening so you can't have
some kind of feedback effects now he's
really arguing that once again oh it's
no problem it will kind of stabilize out
I don't see any reason to believe that a
priori but certainly yes you you have
some pretty sound science there that
says given these assumptions yes you
will have more energy in the system and
that means that you expect to enter a
different regime than you're currently
in which for us is probably not a good
thing not now to your point there are
many many side loops for instance in
climate models probably the least bound
element in the simulations around cloud
formation with increased water vapor in
the atmosphere right and say well why is
that important because clouds are far
more reflective of light then the earth
or the water is so you know if cloud
formation as water vapour cycles operate
faster and faster in the atmosphere as
temperature starts to rise a little bit
it is possible the cloud formation could
be the adapter that essentially
constrains the system but the best
models we have show that while it makes
a significant difference in the rate of
run-up it is nowhere near enough to stop
the run-up at least that's the models
I'm familiar with the other second
biggest one is the absorption of co2
into the oceans now that's only a
short-term fix because the long-term
problem is let's assume somehow
magically which does not appear to be
correct from the physical chemistry that
all the co2 excess co2 is absorbed the
ocean the end result is an acidic ocean
with all kinds of dire effects right you
know I think that's for whatever reason
that's been one of the more downplayed
aspects of the danger is the
acidification of oceans and what that
means for coal earth ecosystems and then
of course in this particular case we'll
talk about the
cautionary principle in general later
but in the area of climate there's also
side loops and we can see in the
geological record that it's happened
where we could move from you know
worst-case scenario 5 degrees C by 2100
to 15 degrees C by 2100 if we get into a
positive feedback loop for instance
there are methane ices in shallow waters
all around the world methane is kind of
an odd gas and that it solidifies into
an Isis surprisingly low pressure and of
course it's a triple point with pressure
and temperature and if the water
temperatures rise in those shallow
waters enough to let loose those methane
ices there's huge quantities of a much
more than the amount of methane known to
be available natural gas wells that
could cause a very rapid run eopns and
they say it's a small rapid run-up but
if it turns out there's lots of these
ices methane ices at low depths of the
water and they're not have not been
fully mapped you could get a positive
feedback loop where a sharp but
relatively small rise in temperature
causes more methane ices to evaporate
into the water and bubble up into the
air and we could rapidly spin up to
something like a 15 degree C 25 26
degree F increase by 2100 which would be
truly disastrous and so the nature of
our system with the side loops that
could drive positive feedback as a
particular reason to consider the
precautionary principle yeah absolutely
and obviously there are potential as you
put them side loops that have negative
feedback but really that's what we're
not sure about you've mentioned this one
particular one how many have we not
identified yet how many potential sort
of positive feedback loops points of
instability are there lurking that we
know nothing about right now and we
don't want to find out the hard way we
do know from the geological record that
it has happened from the Greenland ice
cores we have found periods where
temperatures have jumped 15 C in 50
years that would be catastrophic
interesting well let's talk about their
precautionary principle I read carefully
your paper on GMOs mm-hmm I will say
it's a paper on precautionary principle
and we we use the application as GMOs as
an example case yeah
killer powers a counterexample case and
i will say i walked into it with a
farmer's bias that sounds like
right but on the other hand by time I
was finished reading and I said mmm
maybe they're right but I'd like to
probe into that one a little bit and see
if we can clarify my thinking and maybe
yours why don't you tell the story and
use it from the GMO perspective and
maybe if you want to compare and
contrast with nuclear on the story were
telling of that paper we've been doing
for a long time frankly a corporate
talking point is sort of we've been
modifying organisms forever which is
true we've been doing it from an
artificial selection standpoint now what
is happening with GMO is this kind of
top-down design thinking where we're
saying okay we have this ability to say
insert trans genes into organisms and
elicit desirable properties and then use
those as cultivars in agriculture so
there's actually quite a few problems
here but one of the fundamental issues
is that these designs that these folks
are imagining these sort of whole system
design of kind of reimagining every
facet of Agriculture are making a lot of
simplifying assumptions around what the
complexities of Agriculture actually are
and the way complex systems work and how
they push back on things so just as a
very sort of well-known example
herbicidal resistance is often
engineered into these organisms well lo
and behold the herbicide is used a lot
on these crops so that the crops live
and the weeds die well the weeds evolve
herbicide resistance right so there's
these assumptions that aren't built into
their top-down design that they're now
reacting to but are not something they
imagined happening there's other issues
specific issues like the fact that you
know they claim the pesticide usage
levels are way down but they're not
accounting for the fact that all of
these organisms are generating producing
bt pesticides inside of them inside of
each cell endogenously producing these
proteins so the idea that the count of
application is down doesn't represent
what's actually in there and that
specifically has the
of what you can't wash that off and
other problems as well as you know
what's happening to the pollinator
populations these are designed to
service insecticides for these crops so
those are some specific issues the
general issue is we are tinkering with
we are playing with you're trying to
design systems within ecosystems where
runaway cascade effects can happen in
ecosystems they do happen and we're now
doing long-range you could call it
long-range transport of features of
biology protein synthesize that can have
massive effects on the ecosystems
they're inserted to so as we address in
the paper the idea isn't that the
activity of modifying the organism is in
and of itself dangerous or risky the
issue is we are without any sense of the
potential cascade effects we are
releasing these into the environment and
we're not doing it on a small scale
we're in a large-scale synchronized
fashion releasing novel organisms into
the environment and when we're thinking
about the potential for Cascades a
ecological cascade or viral cascade or
epidemic cascade you know you think of
the Irish potato famine as an example of
where a cascade can really have an
effect on crops there's no clear upper
bound at which if we move into a space
with these kinds of effects at which
they'll stop and when you end up with
because you have these potential for
contagion you have this potential for
cascade you end up with fat-tailed
distributions as opposed to thin tail
ones meaning very large events can
happen and those events are almost
certainly not in our favor and there's
no obvious upper bound at which if
something like that did start to unfold
there would be a kind of circuit breaker
you might call it or like a boundary
that causes the process to stop and so
the idea isn't to predict one or other
feature that is the major problem but to
recognize that we're playing in a space
with living organisms that have all of
the features that contribute to
cascading have fat tails and we're now
going above and beyond
the statistical search space of
artificial selective processes where
selecting this tomato over that tomato
and growing from that seed we're now
saying I think Tomatoes should be
resistant to this pest and they should
generate this pesticide so that this
pest can't get them and injecting that
across a huge number of tomatoes that
are all very genetically similar and
projecting it actively worldwide and
replacing other more time-tested systems
with these kinds of systems as another
kind of bonus risk and so the idea is
okay we're definitely in a systemic
regime where fat tails exist we
definitely don't have the analytic nor
modeling and simulation tools to
exhaustively look at the possible
trajectories of this we're not treating
this as a risk to environmental exposure
but we are exposing the environment to
it in a massive way and so you start to
stack up these different features and
you see that this is a situation where
we're imagining these benefits you know
I hate the corporate talking points
because they're they're frankly
unethical but you know oh don't you want
to feed the world is this can feed the
world and your way won't for whatever
reason even though that's obviously a
straw man there's a lot of different
approaches that don't pose the same risk
that could indeed feed the world
so you're stacking all of these risks up
and you're pointed to these benefits and
the fact of the matter is that when you
have these potential downsides
there's no finite amount of benefits you
can kind of articulate and tack on that
justify taking the risk of collapsing
ecosystems which we all depend on which
agriculture depends on which we depend
on for so many of our life-support
systems this is where I want to push
back a little bit right we quickly were
able to describe some very serious
ecosystem risks around climate now
positive feedback loops historical
records etc and we also talked about
negative feedback loops that might
ameliorate it when we think about GMOs I
have yet to see a compelling causal
story on how a GMO plant could cause
widespread devastation in the ecosystem
let's think you know one example ok I'll
take the example let's use cotton it's
the
number one GMO planet if you have
another one we can use corn cotton soy
these are the ones that are at mostly
mono crop so obviously you have at the
level of human nourishment the ability
to eat you have the risks of massive
amounts of monoculture coming out of
this sort of unprecedented levels of
monoculture now monoculture is a risk
regardless of GMO but GM overly
exacerbates the degree of monoculture
that we're talking about here we're
talking globally so if you did have some
kind of a viral event or any kind of
pathogen event this can spread now
worldwide and the effect on our food
system our food supply could be massive
and imagine all the other interconnected
interdependent human systems once the
food system starts to be stressed that
hard okay so so there's one let's stop
there because what you just described is
the danger of monoculture not the danger
of GMO and we had horrendous monoculture
long far back as we probably know like
95% of our bananas they're all clones of
one banana it's astounding and apples
were way more monoculture than they are
now I never blew mostly eaten apples nor
mostly in bananas but more and more we
are mostly eating corn mostly eating soy
and we're talking about these crops and
the GMO in this case is a enabler of a
degree of monoculture that didn't exist
before at least early before you know
the patents expire etc it may actually
drive diversity if people take different
GMO approaches so I would say you're
arguing against the monoculture which I
strongly agree with we can have a
wonderful conversation about that it may
be that GMO is an accelerant but it is
not I would say in the in this leaf
first argument not the fundamental well
you say it could be an accelerant but
but as we know well from complex systems
science more is different so when you
when you speed something up that quickly
you can quickly end up in a
qualitatively different regime and
that's what we're positing we're
experiencing with this so yes you can
get
there other ways but getting there
faster implies much more risk the one
could throw out a counter way to
regulate right rather than to be in
Europe and banning GMOs let's say we can
have an anti Monaco to rule we can
require that no more than 20% of any
grain crop can be within X DN a has a
Hamming distance of the rest of the crop
and so force diversity rather than ban
the technology you could what you'll
find I mean in a realistic application
that so let's say we wanted that as a
policy what what would happen well the
value proposition to global corporations
would drop rapidly because their whole
value prop is really about this it's
actually hard to develop a GMO line so
they kind of every once in a while
something that makes sense for their
profit model and they deploy it in sync
so you would experience a lot of
pushback on that policy via regulatory
capture from these large corporations so
just in terms of real-world
implementation of a policy like that so
let's imagine that somehow we could get
such a policy implemented
I agree that'd be a great mitigant would
that mitigate all of the risks of GMO no
not necessarily
we have other issues like crossbreeding
things are promiscuous in nature you
know from bacteria to plants and there
is very good evidence of these traits
not staying confined into the the crops
themselves but actually crossbreeding
into wild grasses and things for
instance is a very interesting study in
Switzerland that has had from you know
day 0 a total ban on the cultivation or
import of GMO and what you find are
grasses that have cross bred and have
these traits along the train tracks
while Y along the train tracks because
there's some kind of a pollination event
that's happening the trains travel
themselves so there's all these kinds of
dynamics that we're not factoring in
about how things spread and when we're
talking about spreading these traits
well what traits well there's some
frankly propaganda around oh they could
be traits that are for drought tolerance
and they could be traits for you know if
I
so that people don't go blind and things
but in reality the only traits that have
found any utility are herbicidal
resistance and insecticide production
and so we could imagine a different
universe in which some other trait is
discovered now when we go back to the
this is a little different no free lunch
than we were talking about before but
there's no free lunch in terms of you
know you're gonna engineer and drought
tolerance well well something's gotta
give so what does that mean a lot of the
stuff is more fantastical than practical
but in essence we're talking about
systems that can do many things so mono
crop is one of the features
crossbreeding and spreading proteins and
amplifying certain proteins that might
say service and secta size throughout an
ecosystem present another source of
systemic risk so we need pollinators I
don't really buy the idea that we can
replace all their pollinators with
little robots and everything will be
fine
we need these ecosystems cyclers and
connector nodes and pollinators are a
huge one of those and we're also now
we're having wild plants that are
growing insecticide in ways that no
other plant was growing them before and
now plants in general do often have
insecticidal qualities but you're
presenting a very novel exposure in
short order in a way that doesn't
respect something we talked about before
the co-evolutionary dynamics of
ecosystems
now ecosystems generally play nice
precisely because there's so much
coevolution happening as an example of a
non GMO issue that we all recognize that
is related to this is invasive species
why are invasive species invasive you
were talking about those weeds well it's
because they're now in a new context
that they weren't in before and so they
lacked the co-evolutionary history of
that ecosystem and so there's not a
proper push and pull that develops over
time so how does that proper push and
pull develop it's the coevolution and
frankly small local extinction events
when coevolution doesn't satisfy you
know when it ends up in a kind of
Malthusian extinction and so it's
somehow something undercuts its own
resource or assumption set of survival
and so without this
illusionary process we're really playing
with fire here and it's not just
monoculture it's systemic perturbation
of ecosystem functioning that's possible
but let's say there's a hop it to a
specific grass in a specific region back
to your paper wouldn't that fall into
the limited category say it's a specific
grass that lives at a certain elevation
in the highlands of Central Europe in
Switzerland right if that is what
happens yes
but the issue is we can't exhaustively
say all the ifs that might occur with
this and we are certainly in a space
where massive spread beyond such bounds
are possible so there is every
possibility in the world that yes some
event could happen that would then be
contained and bounded of course you know
this is inherent in the idea of say a
power-law distribution there's many many
many many many small events what the
problem is is that every once in a while
you have a very very big event and these
are what we're worried about not the
many small events I did like that part
of your argument and I will say it will
cause me to think about this more but I
would say I'm not yet convinced because
I will put the challenge back to you and
the people you work with to come up with
a causal mechanism by which plant based
pasts could go out of control on a
worldwide basis as opposed to perhaps do
some damage to a local ecosystem where a
given species in which there was a Hopf
occurred but we know no plant species
are ubiquitous around the world well the
thing that's changing that is our
agriculture and our international
transport so more and more we are
getting species that are very widespread
crops that are very widespread with very
little genetic diversity so I appreciate
the pushback frankly I think it's always
good to kind of sharpen the sword and to
question one's assumptions another
relevant piece that comes to mind with
respect to the precautionary principle
and how we're presenting it is what is
the supposed problem that this
innovation is addressing or this
intervention is addressing and are there
other ways that present a lot less
uncertainty to address this and in the
case of agriculture there is all the
promise in the world of other approaches
not only don't present the risks that
GMO presents but also have a lot of
other positive externalities that
mitigate a lot of other risks we face
for instance around soil erosion and
things of that nature and you know that
feeds back into carbon sequestration and
all these other issues so it's not only
that there's risks it's that we have
alternatives that don't present the same
risks yeah I would agree with that now
would be a wonderful discussion and at
some point in the future I'm going to do
a whole month on forward-thinking
agriculture now maybe I'll have you back
we can talk just about this topic
unfortunately Joe we're out of time as
has been a wonderful conversation and
everything I was hoping it would be and
I really like to thank you for being on
the Jim Rutte show I want to thank you
for inviting me this has been a lot of
fun no I always appreciate talking to
Jim and I hope we talk soon and you know
on the show or otherwise thanks Joe it's
been great and we'll talk soon
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
Stanton media lab music by Tom Muller at
modern space music.com
[Music]
you